<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks | Eduardo Arnold</title><link>https://earnold.me/talk/</link><atom:link href="https://earnold.me/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 18:30:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://earnold.me/images/icon_hu86725dfa3481f0beabea4a23db3db448_10764_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</title><link>https://earnold.me/talk/</link></image><item><title>IET Talk - Challenges and Opportunities in Connected and Autonomous Vehicles</title><link>https://earnold.me/talk/iet2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 18:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://earnold.me/talk/iet2020/</guid><description>&lt;p>This talk was presented with my colleague Dr Graham Lee who is a lead engineer with the Intelligent Vehicles group at WMG.
Autonomous vehicles are set to transform the worldwide economy. This presentation will highlight the challenges and opportunities in the development and deployment of autonomous vehicles. Exploring the role of connectivity between vehicles and infrastructure is key to achieve full autonomy. Novel research in platooning, cooperative perception and trajectory negotiation will be discussed along with methods for testing and validation of autonomous driving functions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cooperative perception for 3D object detection in challenging driving scenarios using infrastructure sensors</title><link>https://earnold.me/talk/brumai2019/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2019 18:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://earnold.me/talk/brumai2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Detecting people using depth frames and deep classifiers</title><link>https://earnold.me/talk/dsfloripa2019/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2017 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://earnold.me/talk/dsfloripa2019/</guid><description>&lt;p>A short talk about a project I took part during my internship at Instituto SENAI de Tecnologia and which was also my final year project for my undergraduate program. My contribution was to create an automatic human detection system for complex industrial environments. We used depth images from a overhead camera position to perform detection.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Two approaches to the detection problem were implemented and evaluated: traditional learning algorithms with manual feature extraction and deep learning classifiers. During this talk I revealed details and tradeoffs of both methods as well as a quantitative evaluation of their performance.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Computer vision with Python and OpenCV</title><link>https://earnold.me/talk/tdc2016/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://earnold.me/talk/tdc2016/</guid><description>&lt;p>A presentation introducing computer vision concepts and show how one can easily develop interesting applications such as augmented reality with Python. It was focused on implementation details for developers and was presented together with William Jamir Silva.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The code can be divided into two sections, one focusing on computer vision and another on computer graphics. The first one uses image processing algorithms to extract the position and identification of markers put in front of a camera. The latter one uses such information to render 3D models over the marker in the image in real time.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>